现在我们理解了对抗选择明文攻击的安全性
我们来构建加密机制
Now that we understand chosen plaintext
security, let's build encryption schemes
它们对选择明文攻击是安全的
第一个这样的加密机制
that are chosen plaintext secure. And the
first such encryption scheme is going to
叫做密码分组链接模式
密码分组链接模式是这么工作的
be called cipher block chaining. So here
is how cipher block chaining works.
密码分组链接模式使用一个分组密码
以实现对选择明文攻击是安全的
Cipher block chaining is a way of using a
block cipher to get chosen plaintext
特别地，我们看使用初始向量IV的
密码分组链接模式
security. In particular, we are going to
look at a mode called cipher block chaining
CBC是密码分组链接模式的缩写
那么假设我们有一分组密码
with a random IV. CBC stands for cipher
block chaning. So suppose we have a block
EB是一分组密码。那么现在我们定义CBC为如下加密机制
cipher, so EB is a block cipher. So now
let's define CBC to be the following
当需要加密明文m是
encryption scheme. So the encryption
algorithm when it's asked to encrypt a
首先选择一个随机的初始向量IV
message m, the first thing it's going to do
is it's going to choose a random IV that's
IV大小就是分组密码的一个分组大小
所以IV就是一个密码分组
exactly one block of the block
cipher. So IV is one cypher block.
对AES的IV将是16字节
So in the case of AES the IV
would be 16 bytes. And then we're
然后我们这里运行这个算法
我们选择的IV将和第一个明文分组
gonna run through the algorithm here, the
IV basically that we chose is gonna be XORed
进行异或，然后得到的结果
to the first plain text
block. And then the result is gonna be
会使用分组密码进行加密，
输出的就是第一个分组的密文
encrypted using the block cipher and
output of the first block of the ciphertext.
现在到链接部分了，我们使用第一个分组的密文
And now comes the chaining part
where we actually use the first block of
来遮蔽第二个分组的明文
the ciphertext to kind of mask the second
block of the plaintext. So we XOR
所以我们把两者异或，将得到的结果进行加密
就得到了第二个分组的密文
the two together and the encryption of
that becomes the second ciphertext block.
一直下去，等等。。这就是密码分组链接模式
And so on, and so on, and so forth. So
this is cipher block chaining, you can
可以看到密码分组被链接起来，密文
与下一分组的明文进行异或
see that each cipher block is chained and
XORed into the next plaintext
最后的密文将是我们选择的IV
block, and the final ciphertext is going to
be essentially the IV, the initial IV
以及所有密文分组。我应该说一下，IV代表
that we chose along with all the ciphertext blocks. I should say that IV stands
初始向量。我们将看到这个术语是经常使用的
for Initialization Vector. And we're going to
be seeing that term used quite a bit,
每次在加密的开始，
我们都需要随机选取某些东西
every time we need to pick something at
random at the beginning of the encryption
我们一般称之为初始向量IV
scheme typically we'll call that an IV
for initialization vector. So you notice
大家注意这个密文有点比明文长
that the ciphertext is a little bit
longer than the plain text because we had
因为我们必须把IV包含在密文里
要包含这种加密中使用的随机性
to include this IV in the ciphertexts
which basically captures the randomness
那么第一个问题是
that was used during encryption. So the
first question is how do we decrypt the
我们如何解密CBC加密？我再提醒大家一下
results of CBC encryption, and so
let me remind you again that if when we
当我们加密第一个明文信息分组时，
我们把它与IV异或
encrypt the first message block we
XOR it with the IV, encrypt the
加密结果，就得到了第一个密文分组
那么我问大家如何解密？
result and that becomes the first ciphertext
block. So let me ask you how would
给定第一个密文分组
you decrypt that? So given the first
ciphertext block, how would you recover
如何还原第一个明文分组呢？
解密和加密其实是很相似的
the original first plaintext block? So
decryption is actually very similar to
我把解密电路写在这了，大家看到
encryption, here I wrote down the
decryption circuit, you can see basically
除了在底下异或，不是上面，其他基本上是一样的
it's almost the same thing except the XOR
is on the bottom, instead of on the top, and
大家发现我们去掉解密过程中的IV
again you realize that essentially we
chopped off the IV as part of the
我们只输出最初的明文，IV被解密算法丢弃了
decryption process and we only output the
original message back, the IV is dropped
好，那么下面的定理告诉我们
by the decryption algorithm. Okay, so the
following theorem is going to show that in
事实上带IV的CBC模式对选择明文攻击是语义安全的
fact CBC mode encryption with a random IV
is in fact semantically secure under a
我们说得更清楚些
chosen plaintext attack, and so let's
take that more precisely, basically if we
如果我们从一个PRP出发，换句话说
我们的分组密码E定义在空间X上
start with a PRP, in other words, our
block cipher E, that is defined over a
那么我们最后获得的加密算法Ecbc
space X, then we are gonna to end up with
a encryption algorithm Ecbc that takes
输入长度为L的明文，输出L+1长度的密文
messages of length L and outputs
ciphertexts of length L+1. And then
然后假设我们有一个攻击者进行了Q次
选择明文的询问
suppose we have an adversary that makes q
chosen plaintext queries. Then we can
然后我们可以声称下面这个关于安全性的事实
对每一个这样的攻击Ecbc的攻击者
state the following security fact, that
for every such adversary that's attacking
存在一个攻击分组密码PRP的攻击者
Ecbc, to exist an adversary that's
attacking the PRP, the block cipher, with
下面的两个攻击算法之间的关系成立
the following relation between the two
algorithms, in other words, the advantage
换句话说，算法A对加密机制的优势
小于算法B对最初PRP的优势
of algorithm A against the encryption scheme
is less than the advantage of algorithm B
加上一些噪声项。那么我们来解释这个定理
against the original PRP plus some noise
term. So let me interpret this theorem for
通常，这意味着由于E是一个安全的PRP
you as usual, so what this means is that
essentially since E is a secure PRP this
这一项是可忽略的，我们的目标是让
攻击者A的优势也是可忽略的
quantity here is negligible, and our goal
is to say that adversary A's advantage is
但是，这里我们还不能这么说
also negligible. However, here we are
prevented from saying that because we got
因为我们有这个多余的误差项
这一般叫做误差项
this extra error term. This is often
called an error term and to argue that CBC
为了论证CBC的安全性，我们必须确保
误差项也是可忽略的
is secure we have to make sure that the
error term is also negligible. Because if
因为右边的两项都是可忽略的
它们的和也是可忽略的
both of these terms on the right are
negligible, there sum is negligible and
因此A对Ecbc的优势也是可忽略的
therefore the advantage of A against Ecbc
would also be negligible. So this says
这就是说事实上Ecbc是安全的
最好是q^2L^2远远小于|X|的值
that in fact for Ecbc to be secure. It has better
be the case that q squared L squared is
我提醒一下大家这里的q和L是什么
much, much, much smaller than the value X,
so let me remind you what q and L are, so
L是加密的明文长度
L is simply the length of the messages
that we're encrypting. Okay, so L could be
L可以是1000，意味着我们加密的明文
like say a 1000, which means that we are
encrypting messages that are at most 1000
最多有1000个AES分组。q是在CPA攻击下，
攻击者获得的密文数
AES blocks. q is the number of ciphertexts
that the adversary gets to see under the
但在现实中，q的意义是我们使用密钥K
CPA attack, but in real life what q is, is
basically the number of times that we have
加密的次数，换句话说，如果我们使用某个AES密钥
used the key K to encrypt messages, in other
words if we use a particular AES key to
加密了100条明文信息，q=100
这是因为攻击者将会看到
encrypt 100 messages, Q would be 100.
It is because the adversary would then see
用密钥K加密的最多100条信息。
我们来看看这在现实中意味着什么
at most 100 messages encrypted under this key K. Okay
so let's see what this means in the real
我在这里重新写下了定理里的误差
world. So here I've rewrote the error
balance from the theorem. And just to remind
提醒一下大家，使用K加密明文，L是明文分组数
you to use the messages encrypted with K
and L with the lengths of the messages and so
假设我们想让攻击者的优势小于1除以2的32次方
suppose we want the adversary's advantage
to be less than one over two to the thirty
这意味着这个误差项最好小于1除以2的32次方
two. This means that the error term had
better be less than one over two to the
我们来看看用AES时是什么意思
对于AES，当然使用128位分组
thirty two. Okay, so let's look at AES and see
what this mean. For AES, AES of course uses
那么|X|将是2的128次方
128 bit blocks, so X is going to be two
to the 128, the
X的大小将是2的128次方
size of X is going to be 2 to the
128, and if you
如果大家把这个带入到表达式中，可以看出
q和L的乘积最好小于
plug this into the expression you see that
basically the product q times L had
2的40次方。这意味着
better be less than two to the forty eight.
This means that after we use a particular
在我们使用了一个密钥加密了2的48次方个
AES分组后，我们就必须更换密钥了
key to encrypt 2 to the 48 AES
blocks we have to change the key. Okay, so
所以CBC在密钥用来加密2的48次方个不同的AES分组后
不再是安全的了
essentially CBC stops being secure after
the key is used to encrypt 2 to the 48 different AES blocks.
这个安全定理告诉我们这点很好
So it's kinda nice that the security theorem tells
它严格地告诉我们密钥的使用寿命
以及多长时间你需要更换密钥
you exactly how long the key can be used
and then how frequently, essentially, you have to
现在有趣的是，如果你对3DES应用同样的推导
replace the key. Now interestingly if you
apply the same analogy to the 3DES it
3DES的分组要短得多，只有64位。大家看到
actually has a much shorter block, maybe
only 64 bits, you see the key has to be
密钥需要更加频繁地更换，可能每65000个DES分组
需要重新生成一个新的密钥
changed much more frequently, maybe after every
65 thousand DES blocks, essentially you need to generate a new key. So
这是AES拥有更大分组空间的原因之一
this is one of the reasons why AES has a
larger block size so that in fact modes
这样CBC等模式会更安全，人们可以在更长的
时间里使用同一个密钥
like CBC would be more secure and one can
use the keys for a longer period of time, before having
不用去更换之。这意味着必须更换2的16次方个分组
to replace it. What this means is having
to replace two to the sixteen blocks,
每个分组当然是8字节，所以在你加密了
大约半个MB的数据后
each block of course is 8 bytes, so
after you encrypt about half a megabyte of
你必须更换DES密钥，这样速度很慢的
data you would have to change the DES key
which is actually quite low. And you
大家注意到用AES加密的话，在换密钥前
可以加密更多数据。
notice with AES you can encrypt quite a
bit more data before you have to change the
那么我想警告大家，人们在使用带随机IV的CBC时
有一个常见错误
key. So I want to warn you about a very
common mistake that people have made when
当攻击者可以预测IV
using CBC with a random IV. That is that
the minute that the attacker can predict
你加密将使用的这个IV时
the IV that you're going to be using for
encrypting a particular message decipher
这个Ecbc将不再安全。所以当使用带随机IV的CBC时
this Ecbc is no longer CPA secure. So when
using CBC with a random IV like we've
IV的不可预测是重要的。我们来看一个攻击
just shown, it's crucial that the IV is not
predictable. But let's see an attack. So
假设给定一个明文信息的加密
suppose it so happens that given a
particular encryption in a message that
攻击者正好可以预测出加密下一条明文的IV
attacker can actually predict that IV that
will be used for the next message. Well
我们来证明这样子得到的系统对CPA是不安全的
let's show that in fact the resulting
system is not CPA secure. So the first thing the
首先攻击者询问一个明文分组的加密
adversary is going to do is, he is going
to ask for the encryption of a one block
特别地，这个明文分组是0
message. In particular that one block is
going to be zero. So what the adversary
攻击者将获得这个明文分组的加密
gets back is the encryption of one
block, which namely is the encryption of
明文0的加密，再异或上IV
当然攻击者也获得了IV
the message namely zero, XOR the IV. Okay
and of course the adversary also gets the
现在根据假设，攻击者可以预测
IV. Okay so now the adversary by
assumption can predict the IV that's gonna
下一次加密所用的IV，我们也把它称为IV
be used for the next encryption. Okay so
let's say that IV is called, well IV. So
接下来攻击者将会挑战语义安全
next the adversary is going to issue his
semantic security challenge and the
明文m0将变成预测的IV异或上IV1
IV1是用于加密c1的初始向量
message m0 is going to be the predicted IV
XOR IV1 which was used in the encryption
而明文m1仅为一些其他信息
of c1. And the, the message of m1 is just
going to be some other message, it doesn't
具体内容无关紧要。现在我们看当攻击者收到
really matter what it is. So now let's see
what happens when the adversary receives
语义安全挑战的结果时，会发生什么
the result of the semantic security
challenge. Well, he is going to get the
攻击者会得到m0和m1的加密
当攻击者得到m0的加密时
encryption of m0 or m1. So when the
adversary receives the encryption of m0,
告诉我密文c是由什么明文加密的？
tell me what is the actual plain text
that is encrypted in the ciphertext c?
答案是它是由信息IV异或IV1异或用于加密的IV
Well so the answer is that what is
actually encrypted is the message which is
根据预测当然就是IV1
IV XOR IV1 XOR the IV that's used to
encrypt that message which happens to be
所以当攻击者收到了m0的加密时
IV and this of course is IV1. So when the
adversary receives the encryption of m0,
他实际上得到的是IV1的分组密码的加密
he is actually receiving the block cipher
encryption of IV1. And lo and behold,
看，大家注意攻击者已经有了这个值
根据他之前选择明文攻击的询问而来
you'll notice that he already has that
value from his chosen plaintext query.
当攻击者收到明文m1的加密时
And then, when he is receiving the
encryption of message m1, he just received
他刚刚收到一个正常的m1的CBC加密
那么我们发现攻击者
a normal CBC encryption of the message m1.
So you realize that now he has a simple
有一个简单方法来破解这个机制，他只需问
way of breaking the scheme, namely what
he'll do is he'll say, he's gonna ask, "Is the second
第二个密文分组c是否等于选择明文攻击中
收到的询问结果？
block of the ciphertext c equal to the
value that I received in my CPA query?" If
如果是，我说我收到了m0的加密，否则我说
so I'll say that I received the encryption
of m0, otherwise I'll say that I received
我收到了m1的加密。他的测试记为c1，
即c的第二个密文分组
the encryption of m1. So really his test
is c1 he refers to the second block
c11为c1的第二个密文分组，如果两者相等
他就说0
of c and c11 refers to the second block of
c1, if the two are equal he says zero,
否则，他说1。所以攻击者的优势是1
otherwise he says one. So the advantage of
this adversary is going to be 1 and as a
因此攻击者完全破解了这个CBC加密的CPA安全性
result, he completely breaks CPA security
of this CBC encryption. So the lesson here
这里的教训是，如果IV是可被预测的
事实上，加密系统没有CPA安全性
is, if the IV is predictable then, in
fact, there is no CPA security and
不幸都是，这点在实际应用中是个
非常常见的错误
unfortunately, this is actually a very
common mistake in practice. In particular
特别是在SSL协议和TLS1.1中，第I个记录的IV
even in SSL protocol and in TLS 1.1, it turns
out that IV for record number I is in fact
实际上就是第I-1个记录的密文分组
这意味着给定第I-1个记录的加密
the last ciphertext block of record I-1. That means that exactly given
攻击者就可以知道加密第I个记录的IV是多少
the encryption of record I-1, the
adversary knows exactly what IV is going
最近，也就是去年夏天
to be used as record number I. Very
recently, just last summer, this was
这一点被利用，形成了对SSL的一个
非常严重的攻击
actually converted into a pretty
devastating attack on SSL. We'll describe
等我们更多地讨论SSL时，就会描述这个攻击
但现在我们想确保大家理解了
that attack once we talk about SSL in more
detail, but for now I wanted to make sure
当你使用CBC加密时，IV的随机性是非常重要的
you understand than when you use CBC encryption,
its absolutely crucial that the IV be random.
现在我要给大家展示基于新鲜值的CBC加密
Okay, so now I going to show you the nonce based version of CBC encryption
在这种模式里IV被某个不随机但唯一的新鲜值取代
So in this mode the IV is replaced by non random but unique nonce
例如数字1,2,3,4,5，都可以用来做新鲜值
这一模式的好处在于
for example the numbers 1,2,3,4,5, could all be used as a nonce, and now, the appeal of this mode
如果接收方知道新鲜值是多少
is that if the recipient actually knows
what the nonce is supposed to be
就没有必要把新鲜值包含在密文里了
then there's no reason to include the nonce
in the ciphertext, in which case, the ciphertext
密文和明文就一样长了，这与带随机IV的CBC不一样
is exactly the same length as the plaintext,
unlike CBC with the random IV,
那里我们还需要扩充密文以包含IV
这里如果新鲜值已被接收方知道
where we had to expand the ciphertext to include the IV, here, if the nonce is already known to the recipient,
就没有必要把它包含在密文里了
密文和明文就严格地一样长了
there's no reason to include it in the ciphertext, and
the ciphertext is exactly the same length as the plaintext.
使用不随机但唯一的新鲜值固然很好，但是
有一点绝对很重要
So it's perfectly fine to use a non-random but unique nonce. However, it's absolutely crucial to know that,
如果你这样做，在CBC链接使用新鲜值前，还需要再做一步
if you do this, there's one more step that you have
to do before you use the nonce in the CBC chain.
特别地，在这个模式中，我们要使用两个独立的密钥k和k1
In particular, in this mode now we're going to
be using two independent keys, k and k1.
如前所述，密钥k是用来加密单独的明文分组的
The key k is, as before, going to be used to
encrypt the individual message blocks,
而密钥k1是用来加密非随机但唯一的新鲜值的
However, this key k1 is going to be used to
encrypt the non-random but unique nonce,
这样输出将是一个随机的IV，可以被用在CBC链接中
so that the output is going to be a random IV,
which is then used in the CBC chain.
多出来的这一步，使用k1加密新鲜值
是绝对非常重要的
So this extra step here, encrypting the nonce
with the key k1, is absolutely crucial.
没有的话，CBC加密模式不是安全的
Without it, CBC mode encryption would not be secure.
特别是，如果你在CBC中直接使用新鲜值
In particular, if you just directly use the nonce
(接下来一分钟的官方字幕、时间轴全错了，
由ikamusume酱听译)
换句话说，使用新鲜值作为IV
in CBC encryption. In other words, use the nonce
as the IV.
那么我们知道这个非随即的新鲜值不是CPA安全的
then we will know the non-random nonce would not
be CPA secure.
我们上一张幻灯片里已经解决了。事实上，
如果你说k=k1
We solved that on the previous slide. In fact,
if you would say that k=k1
换句话说，你只用密钥k加密新鲜值的话
in other words, you just encrypt the nonce using
the key k
那样也不是CPA安全的，会造成严重的攻击
that is also, well, not gonna be CPA secure, and
can lead to significant attacks
所以我想确保大家理解，如果CBC中的新鲜值不随机
So I want to make sure you understand that if the
nonce in CBC is not random,
这步多出的加密步骤就必须有
this extra encryption step has to take place
and, you know
我要让这多出来的一步跳个舞
以确保大家不会忘记加上它
So I'll make the extra step kind of dance
so that make sure you never forget to put it in.
我会告诉大家，这在实际中是一个极为常见的错误
And I will tell you, this is an extreme
common mistake in practice.
有很多真实的产品和密码学库
There are many real world products and
crypto libraries that actually forget to
忘记在CBC链接中使用非随即新鲜值前加密它了
encrypt the non-random nonce before using it
那实际上造成了一个严重的攻击，例如
in the CBC chain, and that actually leads to a
practical significant attack. For example
在TLS中，这点没有做，因此对TLS里的
CBC加密就有了一个严重的攻击
this was not done in TLS. TLS, as we said,
uses predictable IVs
造成了针对TLS的一个严重攻击
进一步地，这点之所以这么重要
and leads to a significant attack on TLS.
Moreover, the reason it is so important to
是因为事实上很多密码学API是在误导用户
know is that in fact many crypto APIs are
set up to almost deliberately mislead the
去错误地使用CBC。我们来看一看OpenSSL中
user to using CBC incorrectly. So let's
look to see how CBC implemented inside
CBC是如何实现的。在这个函数的参数中
open SSL. So here are the arguments of the
function. Basically this is the plain
这是明文，这是待密文写入的地方
text, this is the place where the cipher
text will get written to. This is the
这是明文长度，这是一个密钥
这里有个参数
length of the plain text. This is a, a Yes
key. Finally there is an argument here that
表示你是想加密还是解密
says whether you are crypting or
decrypting. And the most important
我想指出，这里最重要的参数是IV，但很不幸
parameter that I wanted to point out here
is the actual IV and unfortunately, the
用户需要提供这个IV，然后函数直接使用这个IV
user is asked to supply this IV and the
function uses the IV directly in the CBC
进行CBC加密了。使用前它根本不加密IV
encryption mechanism. It doesn't encrypt
the IV before using it and as a result, if
因此，如果你调用这个函数，并使用非随机的IV
you ever call this function using a non
random IV, the resulting encryption system
得到的加密系统将不是CPA安全的
因此调用这个函数时，这一点很重要
won't be CPA secure. Okay, so it's very
important to know that when calling
CBC加密或OpenSSL提供了一个真随机的IV
functions like this. CBC encryption or
open SSL either supply a truly random IV
或者如果你想将IV设为计数器
那么你需要必须用AES加密计数器
or if you want the IV to be a counter then
you have to encrypt a counter using AES
在调用CBC加密函数之前。必须自己完成加密工作
before you actually call a CBC encrypt and
you have to that yourself. So again, it's
作为编程人员这一点必须做，很重要的
very important that the programmer knows
that it needs to be done. Otherwise the CBC
否则CBC加密是不安全的
关于CBC的最后一点是
encryption is insecure. One last
technicality about CBC is what to do when
当我们加密的明文长度不是分组密码的分组长度的倍数时
the message is not a multiple of the block
cipher block length? That is what do we do
例如，如果最后一个明文分组比AES的分组长度短
if the last message block is shorter than
the block length of AES, for example. So
最后一个明文分组长度比16字节短
the last message block is less than
sixteen bytes. And the answer is if we add
答案是如果我们在最后一个分组后面进行补齐
使之变成16个字节长，与AES分组大小一致
a pad to the last block so it becomes as
long as sixteen bytes, as long as the AES
当然解密时这个补齐部分会被移除
block size. And this pad, of course, if
going to be removed during decryption. So
那么这是一个典型的补齐，这种方式是TLS使用的
here is a typical pad, this is the pad
that is used in TLS. Basically a pad with
用N个字节进行补齐，把这数N写N次
N bytes then essentially what you do is
you write the number N, N times. So for
比如如果大家想补5个字节，就补上字符串55555
example if you pad with five bytes, you
pad with the string 55555. So five bytes
5个字节，每个字节值为5。这个补齐重要的一点是
where each byte is the value five. And the
key thing about this pad is basically when
当解密者收到这条信息时，他看分组的最后一个字节
the decrypter receives the message, what
he does is he looks at the last byte of
假设这个值为5，那么解密者就移除
the last block. So suppose that value is
five, then he simply removes the last five
信息的最后5个字节。问题是如果明文长度
bytes of the message. Now the question is
what do we do if in fact the message is a
正好是16的整数倍，不需要补齐呢？
如果我们不需要补齐
multiple of sixteen bytes so in fact no
pad is needed? If we don't pad at all,
就会有问题，因为解密者也会看最后一个分组的
well that's a problem because the
decrypter is going to look at the very
最后一个字节，是实际信息的一部分
last byte of the last block which is a
part of the actual message and he's going
解密者将从明文中移除很多字节，就会造成问题
to remove that many bytes from the plain
text. So that actually would be a problem.
那么解决方法是，如果不需要补齐
So the solution is, if in fact there is no
pad that's needed, nevertheless we still
我们还是在最后加一个没用的分组，由于
我们加的这个假的分组
have to add a dummy block. And since we
add the dummy block this would be a block
包含了16个字节，每个字节的数值为16
that's basically contains sixteen bytes
each one containing the number sixteen.
好，那我们加16字节的假分组
解密者解密时
Okay, so we add essentially sixteen dummy
blocks. The decrypter, that when he's
他看最后分组的最后一个字节
他会看到16这个值
decrypting, he looks at the last byte of
the last block, he sees that the value is
所以他移除整个分组，剩下的就是明文了
sixteen, therefore he removes the entire
block. And whatever's left is the actual
那么有点不幸的是，如果你在用CBC加密
plain text. So it's a bit unfortunate that
in fact if you're encrypting short
一个短消息，消息正好是32个字节
messages with CBC and the messages happen
to be, say, 32 bytes, so they are a
是16的倍数，那么你必须再加一个分组
multiple of sixteen bytes, then you have
to add one more block and make all these
让所有密文共48个字节，以适应CBC补齐
ciphertexts be 48 bytes just to
accommodate the CBC padding. I should
我应当提一下，有一种CBC变种叫做密文偷窃
mention there's a variant of CBC called
CBC with ciphertext stealing that actually
可以避免这个问题，但我这里先不讲
avoids this problem, but I'm not gonna
describe that here. If you're interested
感兴趣的可以上网查。好
我们关于CBC的讨论先告一段落
you can look that up online. Okay, so
that's the end of our discussion of CBC
下一节我们看如何使用计数器模式
来加密多个信息
and in the next segment we'll see how to
use counter modes to encrypt multiple
使用一个密钥
messages using a single key.